<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true report of a voyage made this last summer by a fleete of 73. shippes, sent forth at the command and direction of the states generall of the vnited prouinces to the coast of Spaine and the Canary-Isles: and in what sort the said fleet tooke the principall town, and two castles of the Grand Canaria; as also an other towne in the island of Gomera: with the successe of part of the saide fleete in their returne homeward. Which set saile for Spaine the 25. of May, and returned home the 10. of Septemb. 1599.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4555.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125292</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898353</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898353</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2059:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true report of a voyage made this last summer by a fleete of 73. shippes, sent forth at the command and direction of the states generall of the vnited prouinces to the coast of Spaine and the Canary-Isles: and in what sort the said fleet tooke the principall town, and two castles of the Grand Canaria; as also an other towne in the island of Gomera: with the successe of part of the saide fleete in their returne homeward. Which set saile for Spaine the 25. of May, and returned home the 10. of Septemb. 1599.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by P. S[hort]. for William Aspley, dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Tygers head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated from the Dutch of Michiel Joostens van Heede--STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's full name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Canary Islands --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133399:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE REPORT of a voyage made this laſt Summer by a fleete of 73. ſhippes, ſent forth at the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and direction of the ſtates generall of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> prouinces, to the coaſt of Spaine and the Canary-Iſles: And in what ſort the ſaid fleet tooke the principall town, and two Caſtles of the Grand Canaria; as alſo an other towne in the Iſland of Gomera: with the ſucceſſe of part of the ſaide fleete in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne homeward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which ſet ſaile for Spaine the</hi> 25. <hi>of</hi> May, <hi>and returned home the 10. of Septemb. 1599.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by P. S. for William Aſpley, dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Tygers head. 1599.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="report">
            <pb facs="tcp:133399:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133399:2"/>
            <head>A true report of a voyage made this laſt Summer, by a fleete of 73. ſhippes, ſent forth at the commande and direction of the ſtates generall of the vnited Prouinces, to the coaſt of Spaine and the Canarie-iſles.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Veſday</hi> the 25. daie of <hi>Maie</hi> the wind being Northe and Northe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt, we in the fleete of <hi>Roterdam,</hi> being 20. ſaile of ſhips, the ſunne beeing ſoutheweſt and by weſt, came before <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> and anke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red neere vnto <hi>Cleiburch;</hi> our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall at his comming found the fleetes North-<hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Zeland</hi> ready.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> the 26. daie wee remained there at anchor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 27. day of <hi>Maie,</hi> we tooke into our ſhips (by the Generals commandement) two gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and foure ſouldiours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friday</hi> the 28. of <hi>May,</hi> 1599. the wind being nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly, we waied our anchors, and ſailed from the <hi>Weelings</hi> with 73 ſhips, hauing faire weather, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our courſe weſt, ſouthweſt. Wee had 3. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals in this fleete, whereof the chiefe Admirall was the ſhip of <hi>William Derickſon Cloper,</hi> wherein was imbarked the honourable gentleman <hi>Peter Van Doeſt</hi> being generall of the fleete. This ſhip was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:133399:3"/> called the <hi>Orange,</hi> carying in her top a flag of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range colour, vnder whoſe ſquadron were certaine Zelanders, with ſome ſouth and north Hollanders; <hi>Ian Geerbrantſon</hi> caried the white flag, vnder whom the Zelanders and ſhips of the <hi>Maze</hi> were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And <hi>Cornelius Gheleinſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of <hi>Vlyſhing</hi> wore in his maine top the blew flag, vnder whom were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted certaine ſhips of the <hi>Maze</hi> with ſome north Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers. Thus were wee deuided into ſundry ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, but to what ende it was ſo done, it is to me, and many others vnknowne.</p>
            <p>Saturday the 29. of <hi>Maie,</hi> hauing ſight of <hi>Callis,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhips lay to the lee ward, &amp; ſtaied for the rereward. The Lord generall ſhot off a peece, and afterward hung out the princes flag, in ſigne that the captains ſhold come aboord him, preſently al the captains en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into their boates, &amp; rowed aboord y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> General, at which time were two pinnaces ſent out of the fleet, whereof one was the Generals Pinnace, but vnto what place they ſailed, wee were altogether igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. And when the boates rowed from the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſome of them went aboord the victualers, and tooke out of them certaine fire workes. The ſunne ſouthweſt, the Generall diſcharged another peece of ordinance, and put out the Princes flag, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon preſently the captaines went aboord him, and when our captaine returned, he had in his hande a letter cloſed vp, which hee brought from the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and wee imagined that euery captaine had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the like, and then wee ſailed altogether to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the higth of <hi>Blackneſſe,</hi> where wee anchored, (which cauſed vs greatly to wonder, ſeeing we had ſo faire a wind,) but we perceiued afterwards, that this was done, to the ende we ſhould there abide the comming of the great new ſhip of <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> for the ſoldiours which were appointed for her, were all with vs in a ſhip of our company.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:133399:3"/>
            <p>Sunday, the 30. of <hi>Maie,</hi> where lying at anchor al that night, the next morning we ſet ſaile altogether hauing the winde at north eaſt, wee ſet our courſe weſt north weſt, the weather being faire. The ſame morning our captain read vnto vs thoſe very arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which before had bin read vnto vs in the prince <hi>Mauritz</hi> his Court, and afterwards we altogether, and with one accord were ſworne to the keeping of them: At noone wee were neere vnto <hi>Beuerſier,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a fine gale out of the eaſt north eaſt, the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was calme, the formoſt ſhippes ſlacked their ſailes, attending the comming in of the hindermoſt.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday, the ninth of Iune, by the breake of daie we were hard vnder the coaſt of <hi>Spaine</hi> neere to <hi>Viuero,</hi> the winde being weſterly, we ſailed north weſt and by north, and north northweſt, the ſunne ſouthweſt and by weſt; we were ouer againſt the cape <hi>Ortegael,</hi> we ſailed north weſt and by north, to fetch the wind: we were in 44. degrees 20. minuts, at twilight, we had the foreſaid Cape of vs about 5. miles ſouth weſt and by weſt.</p>
            <p>Thurſday the 10. of <hi>Iune,</hi> the winde being at eaſt ſouth eaſt, wee directed our courſe towardes the ſhore, and might certainly diſcerne that it was the coaſt of <hi>Ortegall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ortegall.</note> we bore in weſt ſouthweſt directly with the land, and ordered all thinges as if we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſhould haue had battell, and about noone wee had ſight of the <hi>Groyne,</hi> namely the tower which ſtandeth neere the <hi>Groine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friday, the 11. of <hi>Iune,</hi> at the breake of day the winde being at north eaſt and by eaſt, ſixe of our ſhips ſailed forwarde ſouth ſouthweſt, meaning to enter the <hi>Groine,</hi> and there to learne how al things ſtood. The ſunne being ſoutheaſt, Cape <hi>Prior</hi> was eaſt from vs, wee bare ſouth, preſently after we ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two boates comming out of <hi>Veroll</hi> to learn what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133399:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhips we were, the rather becauſe that the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had ſeene our fleete at ſea: we ſailed by the wind, and lay in the wind to ſtay for their comming. The one doubting vs woulde not come neere vs, the other boat alſo durſt not approch neere vs: wee called to one of the Spaniardes, ſaying wee came from <hi>Hamborch</hi> laden with cordage &amp; other goods, deſiring and praying him to let vs haue a Pilot to bring vs into the <hi>Groine,</hi> wherewith the boate came aboord vs, ſo that by our great haſte and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie we got one Spaniard, the other which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the boate would not come into our ſhip, but preſently thruſt off their boate, making all poſſible ſpeede to get from vs. Hauing nowe gotten this Spaniarde, hee was preſently deliuered into the handes of the Generall, who confeſſed that there were about 4000. ſouldiours come into the towne, with certaine horſemen, 36. waggons with money, and 300. pipes of wine, to furniſh the Spaniſh fleet, that he lay the night paſt in the <hi>Groine,</hi> and was the kings ſeruant. The ſun ſouth ſouth weſt, we came with our whole fleete before the <hi>Groyne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The whole fleet commeth before the <hi>Groine.</hi>
               </note> where wee found the great newe ſhip of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> vnder the Towne.</p>
            <p>At 12. 13. and 10. fadome we caſt anchor, ſo that wee might behold much people both on the ſhoare &amp; vpon the wals of the town. From the caſtle &amp; town both, they ſhot mightily with their great ordinance into our fleet, ſo that there were aboue 200. cannon ſhot diſcharged, wherewith ſome of our ſhips were hit, but not one man loſt, and little hurt done other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. There lay an other caſtle eaſt ward from the towne, which ſhot alſo moſt terribly, but altogether vncertainly, for we know not that they touched any one ſhip more then <hi>Moy Lambert,</hi> which was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee wondered at, ſeeing our fleete lay ſo thicke
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133399:4"/> together, and ſo neere vnder the caſtle. There laie hard vnder the caſtle 12. great Gallions, with ſome french ſhips, which alſo nowe and then ſhot among our fleete, but they lay ſo neere the walles that wee could do them no harme at all. The Lord Generall worthy of al praiſe, wiſely bethinking himſelfe, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all his captaines and counſell to come aboorde him, that they might together conferre vpon this buſines, and what meanes might beſt bee found, to inuade the towne and the enemy, but they conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, not to meddle with the land there: ſeeing the enemy was there, ſtrong vpon his guard, and that 5. weekes paſt both from <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> &amp; by a French man, they had knowledge of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming; by reaſon of the calme, wee were conſtrained to towe out our ſhips with the boates in diſpite of al their ſhot, thus we parted from the <hi>Groyne</hi> without profit, or effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of any thing, leauing the Papiſts of <hi>Groyne</hi> as wee founde them. From thence (the winde being at ſouth ſouthweſt) wee bent our courſe towarde Cape <hi>Saint Vincent,</hi> meaning to goe to <hi>Saint Lucars,</hi> hoping to fal vpon them at vnawares, and ere they looked for vs.</p>
            <p>Saturday the 12. of <hi>Iune,</hi> hauing got a fine gale we ran along the coaſt of <hi>Galicia,</hi> at noone wee were before the Iland of <hi>Ceſarian,</hi> and ſet our courſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Cape <hi>Finiſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sunday the 13. of <hi>Iune,</hi> the lorde Generall gaue ſharpe commandement by his letters, forbidding al men aboorde the ſhips to vſe any play, with tables, cards, or dice, either for money, or for paſtime, or vpon credit.</p>
            <p>Munday the 14. of <hi>Iune,</hi> the wind blew ſo harde out of the North, that wee could not beare our top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes with our forecourſe which ſailed ſouth, the ſunne was ſouthward, we had Port a Porte of vs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133399:5"/> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in 41 degrees and 20. minuts.</p>
            <p>Tueſday the 15. of Iune, as ſoone as day appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we had ſight of Cape <hi>Roxent,</hi> and then we ſailed making ſmall way, ſtaying for the comming toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the fleete: the wind as before, we ſailed ſouth ſouthweſt, and were in 36. degrees.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday the 16. of Iune, towardes the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning we had ſight of two ſtrange ſhips eaſtward of our fleete, certain of our ſhips made towards them and tooke them, the one was an engliſh man of war; the other was a Spaniſh barke with three miſſens: at his comming before the Generall, he ſaid, he had already ſent 2. priſes into Englande, and woulde now with this priſe returne home: for his victuals were almoſt ſpent.</p>
            <p>Thurſday the 17. of Iune, it was very ſtill and calme weather.</p>
            <p>Friday the 18. of Iune, the wind being at north northeaſt, we ſailed ſouth ſouthweſt. The Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall cauſed all the Captaines with the Pilots to come aboord him: demanding of them which of them was beſt acquainted in the Iles of <hi>Canaria:</hi> and further, by what meanes they might conquer and force the ſaid Ilands, and land their people. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>but noone the captaines were choſen and appointed which ſhoulde commande on lande. The Generall gaue out newe enſignes, to the number of 9. or 10. according to the number of the ſhips. The lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall appointed to each new captaine, an Ancient bearer, a Lieutenant, and other officers, with 130. ſouldiours and mariners, and inſtructions howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of them ſhould gouerne himſelf on the land.</p>
            <p>Saturday the 19. of Iune, the Generall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that the captaines ſhould deliuer out vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals but twice a day, to wit, 6. and 6. to a meſſe: for 6. men, 5. cans of beere of <hi>Roterdams</hi> meaſure euery
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133399:5"/> day, 5. pounde of breade and no more, a cheeſe of 6. l. euery weeke, one pound of butter weekely, likewiſe peaſe, beanes, or Otemeale twiſe a day, according to the order. Captaine <hi>Harman,</hi> and captaine <hi>Pijc,</hi> had each of them commiſſion to commande on the land as captaines ouer two companies of ſaylers, each company containing 130. men. <hi>Harman Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſon</hi> was appointed Ancient to captaine <hi>Henricke Pijc,</hi> and <hi>de Blomme</hi> Ancient to captaine <hi>Hendricke Hertma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> The ancients were deliuered the ſame day.</p>
            <p>The 20. 21. 22. daies, wee ſailed ſouth ſouthweſt, the wind being northerly.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday the 23. of Iune, the wind was north northeaſt. The Generall commaunded all the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines both for the ſea and land to come aboord him, where it was ordained and determined how the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell ſhould be ordered, after they were landed. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the altitude, we found our ſelues to be 36 miles from great <hi>Canaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thurſday the 24. of Iune, we ranne our foreſaid courſe. The ſun being weſt northweſt, we ſawe the land eaſt and by ſouth off vs: wee ſailed eaſt and by ſouth, and with great labour and diligence bore all that might with the land.</p>
            <p>Friday the 25. of Iune, we continued our courſe to the land for our aſſured knowledge thereof, and perceiued it to be <hi>Lancerot;</hi> we ſaw alſo a ſmall land (which lay between both) called <hi>Allegrania,</hi> and alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iland <hi>Forteue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tura,</hi> which is 24. miles great, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward we ſailed ſouthweſt along the coaſt of <hi>Forte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentura,</hi> which is a lande that hath very high hils. The ſun ſouthweſt, we were paſt the Iland <hi>Forteue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tura,</hi> and were ſailed out of ſight thereof, running as yet ſouthweſt: about ii. a clocke in the afternoone wee had ſight of the Iland of great <hi>Canaria,</hi> for a while wee kept our way; but when the Generall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133399:6"/> was aſſured that it was the grand <hi>Canaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The whole Netherlandiſh fleet commeth before the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland &amp; town of Grand Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria.</note> wee all tooke in our ſailes, and lay to the lee ward, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained vntill it was paſt midnight, then wee ſet faile againe and made to the lande, our courſe weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde.</p>
            <p>Saturday the 26. of Iune, in the morning the whole fleet ſailed weſt directly to the land, the winde north and by eaſt, and made all thinges ready to land; being now neere the ſhore, the whole fleete let fall their anchors harde by the great caſtle, which lieth north northweſt from the town, from whence they began to ſhoot mightily againſt the ſhips. The lord Generall and the vize Admirall with the other ſhips that had the greateſt ordenance, anchored cloſe vnder the caſtle, &amp; for a certain time they plied each other with their great ſhot; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Generals main maſt, and his miſſen maſt were ſhot thorow, and his vize Admirall, namely the great new ſhip of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> was ſhot thorow 6. or 7. times; ſo that ſome of the ſouldiours and maryners alſo were ſlaine before they entered their long boates to rowe to the ſhore: But the ſhips for their parts, had ſo well beſtowed their ſhot on the caſtle, that they of the caſtle began to faint, wherby they diſcharged not ſo thicke and often as before. Our men rowed to the land in the long boates, euery one full of ſoldiours, &amp; the ſhips which could not diſcharge their ordenance againſt the caſtle, bent them againſt the ſhore, (for the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had three braſſe peeces lying vpon the ſtrand) and many people were there gathered together where our ſouldiours ſhoulde land. Nowe as ſoone as the Generall with the moſt parte of the long boates were come together, they all at one inſtant rowed toward the ſhore, maintaining for a while the fight on both ſides with their ſhot. But the General per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing that the enemie woulde not abandon the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133399:6"/> place, with a valiant courage made to the ſhore, and altogether leaping into the water vp to the middle, maintained the fight with the enemy. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the enemy no leſſe couragious, would not yet leaue the ſtrond, ſo that ſome of our ſouldiours &amp; mariners loſt their liues before the enemy would retire: for the place was diſcommodious, and hard to lande; but moſt of the enemy were ſlaine, to the number of 30. or 36. and the Gouernor his right leg was ſhot off, ſitting on his horſe. The lord General <hi>Peter von der Doeſt</hi> leaping firſt on land, was thruſt in his leg with a pike, and had in his body 4. wounds more, and was in great danger to haue loſt his life, but that one of the ſoldiours ſlewe the Spaniarde which meant to haue don it; but his wounds were of ſmall moment, and his ancient bearer was ſlain with a ſhot, the Lieutenant Generall was ſhot in his throte, captaine <hi>Kruyc</hi> in the heade, 4. ſoldiours were ſlain, &amp; 15. hurt in the generals pinnace before they could come to land: But when our people now with one courage all together ruſhed vpon the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, (leauing their ordenance behinde them,) they forſooke the ſtrond, and ran together into the town, carying with them their Gouernour, whoſe leg was ſhot off, &amp; he was a Knight of the order of the croſſe, and leauing behind them 36. deade carcaſes on the ſtrond, were preſently by our people ranſacked, and our dead people buried. Our men now hauing won the ſtrond, put themſelues preſently in battell ray; the empty boates returned to the ſhips, but after our people had taken the ſtrond, the caſtle did neuer ſhoot ſhot. After the boates were returned aboord, preſently they rowed againe to the ſhore full of ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours; our people being all landed,<note place="margin">Twenty foure companies ſtrong of the Netherla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders.</note> they which for the firſt time had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, ſet vs in 7. troupes, or battalions, being xxiiii. companies ſtrong, of ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:133399:7"/> and Mariners, with twentie foure Aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes. At which time we marched a little forward twenty one a breſt,<note place="margin">The firſt caſtle taken,</note> and ſtanding altogether in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell; ſuddainly three mariners came running to the Generall, (which had bin at the caſtle) telling him that the Spaniards deſired to deliuer him the caſtle, ſo their liues &amp; goods might be ſaued: the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall with ſome of the captaines and ſouldiours went firſt thither, and preſently the caſtle was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered into his poſſeſſion, hoping on his pitty and mercy, and leauing behind them all the great orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, namely 9. peeces of braſſe, &amp; 6. Iron peeces, &amp; alſo al their weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. In the caſtle were about 80. Spaniards, ſome cannoniers, ſome ſoldiors, and ſome people of the countrey, for the defence thereof; beſide powder, ſhot and match accordingly, for the artillery, and alſo thirty ſmall peeces or caliuers. Alſo wee founde 58. priſoners, the reſt were ſlaine with ſhot in the fury, and ſome were runaway. The priſoners (which our people had taken in the road with two Barkes, and a ſhip ſunke with our orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as they lay all 3. hard before the caſtle) were ſent altogether aboorde the ſhips: except 3. of the principals which the lord General reſerued by him, to the end he might the better knowe the ſtate of all things. Preſently 80. ſoldiours were ſent into the caſtle, who tooke down the kings flag, and ſet vp the princes colours. At the ſame inſtant two Negros were brought to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> General, which were fetched out of the mountains, they ſaid that they had lien there a ſleepe, and knew nothing of any matter. But now when it began to wax dark, we marched altogether a great way towards the town, 4. companies of ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diors approched hard vnder the towne, and other 4. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies had the rereward: thoſe of the <hi>Maze,</hi> with the <hi>Amſterdammers</hi> remained a pretty way from the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133399:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> towne, vnder the hils; and the Zelanders, with the north Hollanders lay neere the waters ſide, ſo wee remained al that night in order of battell.</p>
            <p>Sunday the 27. of Iune, after we had now ſtood al night in battel order, early in the morning we mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al our 7. troupes hard vnder the town of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>narie,</hi> where we remained a while in that order: but becauſe they of the caſtle (which lieth to the towne) ſhot ſo mightily among vs; 2. of the troupes retired vnder a hill, where we were a little freede from the caſtle: for while our people ſtood imbattailed before the town, the caſtle did vs great hurt, for ſomtimes they ſhot fiue or ſixe men with one ſhot, ere we could entrench our ſelues before the caſtle: but after they perceiued that our people had made a ſmall trench againſt the ſhot of the caſtle, they placed on the hill fiue or ſixe ſmall peeces, of braſſe called falconets (which ſhoote about a pounde of pouder) and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they ſhot boules of wood, wherewith in the beginning they ſlew manie of our people: ſo aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagiouſlie had they placed their ordenaunce to ſhoot among vs. Ten or twelue of our Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours ranne vp the hill, whereof the enemy tooke one, and preſently cut him in foure peeces. Our people ſeeing that they ſo tyranouſlie dealte with them, about the euening tooke a Spaniarde priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and vſed him after the ſame maner. The lorde Generall perceiuing that many men were flaine with the ordenance, cauſed fiue peeces of braſſe to bee brought from the caſtle which we had taken the daie before, and toward the euening we beganne to make a battery, and the ſame euening brought into it three peeces, whereof two were placed preſentlie to play vppon the Caſtle, and the hill: but that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening were but fiue or ſixe ſhotte made. While that our men made the batterie, and planted or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133399:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> placed the ordenaunce, the enemy placed his orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in counter-battery: and before our battery could be finiſhed, and the ordenance placed, many of our men were ſhot, among who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Peter vanden Eynde</hi> commiſſioner, had his leg ſhot off, whereof he died within three daies after. After that it was dark, al they which lay there before the towne were againe ſet in order of battel, 15. on a ranke, and ſo remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all that night.</p>
            <p>The 28. of Iune, early in the morning euery man retired to his quarter, and then were two peeces more brought to the battery, which alſo were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently placed on the Rampire, and ſo wee began to ſhoot againſt the caſtle with 4. peeces, and with the fifth we plaied vpon the ſmall ordenance which lay vpon the hils. The enemy in the caſtle laid manie ſackes of wooll, and placed many tonnes or barrels filled with ſtones vpon the caſtle walles, ſuppoſing thereby to make ſome little defence from our orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; but when an Iron bullet chanced to hit the barrels ſo filled with ſtones, it did them mightie hurt, for the ſtones would ſcatter maruailouſlie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, whereby many of them that were in the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle were ſlaine. Our men hauing now with their ſhot almoſt abated the force of the caſtle, 4. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies marched vp the hils, intending to beate the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy from thence, which lay there with the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. But the enemy perceiuing himſelfe to bee aſſaulted on all partes, (for moſt of the ordenance of the caſtle were diſmounted and made vnprofitable, the gate of the towne ſet one fire by the Generals commandement) about noone they forſooke both the caſtle, hill, and town, and with all their wiues, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, money and Iewels, and all other things that they coulde carry with them, fled into the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. Which when our men perceiued, they put
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133399:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> themſelues in order of battell, xv. in a ranke. The lord Generall ſeeing the Spaniards ſhamefullie to flie, cauſed 2. ladders belonging to the enemies, to be brought out of a church which ſtood without the towne, whereof the one was too ſhorte, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding himſelfe with one of the ladders climed vp the walles, one man at once followed,<note place="margin">The ſecond caſtle &amp; town of Grand Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria taken.</note> and by this meanes entered the towne ouer the wals. About noone ſome of our men ran into the caſtle without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reencou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter: the enemy had vndermined the gate, but as we approched the wall, it tooke fire, but not one of our people was therewith hurt. they had alſo ſkattered powder in ſundrie places, but our men themſelues did fire the ſame: and as ſoone as our people were entred the caſtle, the Kinges colours were taken downe, and the prince of <hi>Orenges</hi> ſet vp, and we found fiue peeces of braſſe therein. When wee were all entered into the towne, we put our ſelues againe into order of battell 15. in a ranke in a low ground within the towne: and the ſouldiours which entered the towne by the hils ſide, brought to the Generall a man of <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> which they had taken out of priſon: as ſoone as the Generall ſawe him, he went preſently with him to the priſon, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſome of our captaines, where they found 36. priſoners, which preſently were diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. And further they declared, that the ſpaniards had taken with them 2. priſoners into the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, which were condemned to be burnt, the one was an engliſh man, the other a dutchman, which had lien in the holy houſe. Thus with the helpe of God about noone, wee won the great Iland of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria,</hi> and the town of <hi>Allegona,</hi> battered with their owne artillery, and ſkaled with their owne ladders. Towards the euening wee were quartered in the houſen, thoſe wherein the Generall was, were by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133399:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> writing freed, that no man might take out any goods, in the reſt euery one might go, and take what pillage he could find: but the Spaniards had caried all the beſt things with them into the mountaines, and in the euening all our people entered the town. Euery captaine with his company were ſeuerallie lodged, but yet we appointed watch on the hils, as well as in the towne, for the enemy ſhewed himſelfe often vpon the hils, whereby we were forced to keep very good watch.</p>
            <p>The 29. of Iune, this morning ſome of the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners climed vp the hils, but the enemy (to whom the paſſage were better known, then to our people) ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly ſet vpon them, &amp; killed 20. of them. Towards the euening ſome 300. of our Soldiours marched towardes a ſmall caſtle which lay halfe an houres iourney from the towne: but the enemy ſeeing our people to approch, forſooke the place and fled into the mountaines, our men being aſcended, they founde in the caſtle three braſſe peeces; and after they had appointed a Corporall with certaine ſoldiours to keepe the watch, the reſt returned to the citty. The ſame night the Spaniards tooke one of our ſoldiors appointed for a forlorne Sentinel, whom they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently put to the ſword.</p>
            <p>The laſt of Iune, as ſoone as day appeared, wee began to carry the pillage aboorde belonging to the General, and captaines, as wines and other goods. About noone 3. cheefe men of the Spaniards came to our people, which kept watch on the hils with a flag of truce in their handes, which were ſtraight brought before the Generall, and within a while af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there were 2. more brought vnto him: but after they had bin a while with him they departed again towards the mountaines: and in the euening came other 7. Spaniardes to our watch with a flag of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133399:9"/> truce, deſired to ſpeake with the Generall: but they were ſente backe againe into the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes.</p>
            <p>The firſt day of Iuly, 1599. in the morning (our people being on the hils) 2. Friers with three other Spaniards came vnto vs, deſiring to be brought to the Generall, which our men accompliſhed: but the General denied to talke with them, wherefore they were preſently ſent backe againe from whence they came, for we were then labouring to ſend the goods a ſhipboord. Alſo at that inſtant was a ſermon in the great church of great <hi>Canaria,</hi> made by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of <hi>Yſilmond</hi> with great deuotion, and giuing thanks vnto God for our great victory, deſiring him that it would pleaſe him daily to increaſe the ſame, to the honour of his name: at which Sermon the Lorde Generall was preſent with foure hundred perſons.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Iuly, 1599. wee were forbidden by ſounde of the drum, that no man ſhould go beyond the forlorne ſentenell placed on the Mountaines: and to ſende backe againe into the hilles all ſuch Spaniardes which came with a flag of truce, to ſpeake with the Generall, and to put all ſuch to the ſworde as came with weapons. One of our Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces tooke a Fiſherman fiſhing vnder the Ilande <hi>Forteauentura,</hi> wherin were 7. Spaniardes, which were brought before the General, and prently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to priſon.</p>
            <p>The 3. of Iuly in the morning we began to ſende aboord our ſhips all the bels, ordenance &amp; munition which the enemies had left behinde them, at which time 2000. ſoldiors were appointed to march to the hils, to ſeeke the enemy, which lay hid there with their wiues, children &amp; goods, as they were fled out of the towne: and aſſoone as they approched each
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:133399:10"/> other, they began the fight on both ſides with great courage, but the enemy was forced to flie, beeing better acquainted with the paſſages of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains then our people were. our men returned with the loſſe of ſome 70. perſons: among whom captain <hi>Iacques Dierickſon</hi> with his boatſon were ſlaine: the reſt came into the towne againe into their appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted quarters.</p>
            <p>The 4. of Iuly, in the morning we began to burn the towne, and with pouder blewe vp the caſtle which lay by the towne, and we burned likewiſe all the cloiſters and churches which were without the towne, lying neere the water ſide. The town bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, our people were ſet in battell, and in that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der marched out of the towne, vntill they came to <hi>Gratioſa,</hi> the caſtle, which we firſt tooke, lying about halfe an houres iourney from the towne, where the long boates receiued our men, and caried them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine aboorde. Preſently after wee were departed out of the towne, the enemy entered, endeuoring by all meanes poſſible to quench the fire. And while we were ſhipping our people, the enemy ſhewed him ſelfe ſome times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or 6. in a company, but they durſt not approch vs. The rereward of our men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhipped, we put fire to the caſtle which we tooke firſt, and blew it vp: This done, captaine <hi>Quit</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked himſelfe alſo with his ſoldiours, and pillage which he had taken in the rode, for his ſhip wherein he was before was ready to ſinke.</p>
            <p>The 5. of Iuly, lying in the roade, in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Generall diſcharged two peeces of orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and afterward put out 2. flags of the princes colours, thereby giuing to vnderſtand, that all land captaines, and ſea captaines alſo with one of their Pilots ſhould reſort to him, whereupon preſentlie they all rowed aboorde the Generall; the Pilots
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133399:10"/> which were beſt acquainted with the coaſt, were demanded by the Generall which were the weakeſt Ilands, and where they might moſt commodiouſlie land: Towards the euening captaine <hi>Quvt</hi> his ſhip was fired, and ſuffered to driue towarde the ſtrond. At which time a newe captaine was appointed to captaine <hi>Iaques Dirrikſons</hi> ſhip aforeſaide, who was ſlaine in the mountaines, namely captaine <hi>Kloyers</hi> Lieutenant. And the Generals Clarke of the band was appointed Lieuetenant to captain <hi>Kloyer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 6. of Iuly, by reaſon of the contrary winds, and other inconueniences which happened at this preſent, and alſo becauſe ſuch ſhips, which before were ſent to ſea, and could not returne by reaſon of the contrary windes; we remained in the road, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the caſtle of <hi>Gracioſa.</hi> About noone 4. Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards came out of the towne with a flag of truce to the ſtrond, directly ouer againſt our ſhips, whereof 2. were brought aboorde the Generall in one of our long boates, (the other two with their flag of truce were left behinde on the ſtronde) which remained with the Generall vntil the euening, and then were ſet on ſhore, and ſo the 4. Spaniardes returned to the towne.</p>
            <p>The 7. day riding in the roade, in the morning 4. Spaniards with a flag of peace, came to the ſhore from the towne, directly ouer againſt our ſhips: the fleet ſeeing them, ſent a long boate to the ſhore, and brought the ſaid 4. Spaniards aboord the General, theſe men brought with them the ranſome of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Spaniards, which had deliuered vp the caſtle of <hi>Gracioſa</hi> at the Generals pleaſure, which were ſet to ranſome, euery one according to his habilitie &amp; office: and thus all the Spaniardes which were ranſomed, together with the 4. ſpaniardes which brought the ranſoms, were ſet on ſhore with a long
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:133399:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> boate, and departed to the towne.</p>
            <p>The 8. day of Iuly, two howers after ſun riſing, the Generall with all the ſhips ſet ſaile, carying with him all the Spaniardes that were not ranſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſailing alo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the coaſt of great <hi>Canaria;</hi> in which time <hi>Ian Corneleſſon Zwartekeys</hi> departed this worlde, whoſe leg was ſhot off at the taking of the Iland of great <hi>Canaria.</hi> Hauing nowe ſailed from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hight of the ſaid Iland, which lay ſoutherly from vs, we had ſight of captaine <hi>Hertmans</hi> ſhip, and of 3. others which rode there at anchor: who, ſo ſoone as they perceiued our fleete, waied their anchors, and ſailed along the coaſt with vs, which were the ſhips that the Generall had ſent to ſea. Sailing thus together vntill the ſun was in the weſt, the wind began to riſe more and more, ſo that we coulde not keep our direct courſe, but were forced to put to the ſouthweſt of the great Iland of <hi>Canaria,</hi> where we anchored: wee had ſight of the Iland <hi>Teneriffa,</hi> and of an other of the Ilands of <hi>Canaria,</hi> wherein is the hie mountaine called the <hi>Pyck.</hi> This hil was from vs 14. miles, but by the great hight thereof it ſeemed to bee within foure or fiue miles off vs, but in the daie time when the ſun ſhined wee could not ſee it.</p>
            <p>The 9. of Iuly, lying thus at anchor, in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning moſt of the long boates went a ſhore to fetch freſh water, ſuch as they could there find, and caried with them the deade corps of <hi>Ian Corneleſſon</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, the Conſtables ſon of the Admiralty of <hi>Roterda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> called <hi>Zwertkeys,</hi> which was there honorably bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on the high and drie land. This done, we ſet on fire the woode which lay on the ſhore piled and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the woods, but in this place we found not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Spaniards.</p>
            <p>The tenth of Iuly, the boates being all returned
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:133399:11"/> to their ſhips with their people, euery one wayed their anchors and hoiſed their ſailes, the winde at northweſt; but being vnder ſaile together, the wind ſlacked, &amp; by reaſon of the great, calme the ſhips lay a drift for want of wind.</p>
            <p>The 11. of Iuly, in the morning it blewe a ſtout gale in our topſailes out of the northeaſt, but as we approched the Iland of <hi>Teneriffa,</hi> the winde altered often; ſixe or ſeuen of our ſhippes, and the reſt which were next vnto the ſhore, had ſometimes a gale in their topſailes, and ſometimes againe without wind: ſo that we lay a drift, and could keepe no rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning either of the wind or courſe, and were forced to alter our courſe more then 12. times a day.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>A declaration of the taking of <hi>Gomera</hi> one of the Ilands in <hi>Canaria,</hi> and how we afterwardes left it.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He 12. day of Iuly ſailing thus with great variety of wind, vnder the great Ila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Teneriffa,</hi> the day appearing, we had the wind more certain, filling our topſailes with a full gale from the northweſt: And when it was faire day light, we ſaw our fleet ſcattred far one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, by meanes of the foreſaid mutable windes. Some ſhips lay driuing by reaſon of the calme, and other ſome had a little gale, but the moſt part of our fleet were weſt of vs, towards whom with all ſpeed, we with the reſt of the ſhips made. Being al come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee endeuored to reach the Ilande <hi>Gomera,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:133399:12"/> wherein is a little towne: towardes the euening many of our ſhips were neere the Iland, but the moſt part were to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lee ward; ſo that before it grew toward the euening none of vs could come neere the towne. Notwithſtanding in the twilight and ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp of the euening: <hi>Ian Garbrantſon</hi> Admirall of the white flag, his vize Admirall, and a Pinnace following, were come neere the town. Thus the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral ſayling ſo neere to the Iland, they of <hi>Gomera</hi> diſcharged 2. pieces at him, but touched him not. the ſaide Admirall ſeeing this, paſſed on a little farther with the other ſhips which were neere him, &amp; then tooke in their ſailes, and caſt their anchors. The other ſhips which were behinde, laboured all they might to come alſo vnder the Iland to them.</p>
            <p>The 13. of Iuly, the Admiral of the white flag ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus at anchor neere to <hi>Gomera,</hi> the greateſt part of the fleete were yet in the morning betweene the Iland of <hi>Teneriffa</hi> and <hi>Gomera,</hi> ſo that parte of the ſhips were beyonde the towne, and muſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times caſt about to conducte the others in, which were in the lee of vs. When wee had nowe for the moſt part paſſed the hight of the Iland, the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gaue a ſigne to all captaines to come aboorde him, being vnder ſaile, directing his courſe to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of <hi>Gomera,</hi> and the other ſhips did their inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to follow him, and anchored about the necke of the vality, lying north north eaſt off the towne. The ſhips being all come to anchor, the captaines ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red preſently into the long boates, and rowed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boorde the Generall to know his minde: And after they had beene a while in the Generals ſhip, they returned to their ſhips, and 4. companies of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours were choſen out, and landed in the valley. Which done, al the ſhips waied their anchors, and ſailed directly toward the towne, and then came to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:133399:12"/> anchor againe. After that all our ſhips lay thus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the road neere the valley, before the town: we diſcharged certaine peeces againſt the town, but they made no ſhewe at all of reſiſtaunce; for they had buried foure braſſe peeces as ſoone as they had ſight of vs, which lay on the ſtrond neere vnto a ſmall caſtle; the other ſixe companies were alſo ſet on land in the long boates, without any reſiſtance: for the Spaniards with their wiues, children,<note place="margin">The towne of Gomera aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by the Spaniards.</note> and all their goods which they coulde carry with them were fled into the mountains. The firſt 4. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies that were landed, as they marched along the hils ſide towards the towne, perceiuing that the enemy fled with all his goods towards the hils, ſent out a certaine number of ſoldiours to intercept them, and to take from them the goods which they caried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And to accompliſh this enterpriſe, our ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours deſcended the hill into the valley, meaning ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly to ſet vpon the Spaniardes; but the enemie perceiuing their intent, hid themſelues in caues which were neere vnto them, vntill our ſouldiours were in the valley. The ſpaniardes perceiuing that they were ſtrong enough to encounter with our people, ſuddainly leapt out of their dens, and beſet our ſouldiours on both ſides. Our people ſeeing themſelues thus compaſſed with their enemies,<note place="margin">Eighty Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers and diuers Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards ſlaine.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued themſelues moſt valiantly, ſo that many of the ſpaniards loſt their liues, and 80 of ours were ſlaine in this valley: among whom were 2. Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants (the one was <hi>Meerbecks</hi> ſonne, and the other was Lieutenant to captaine <hi>Bynon</hi>) which had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued aboue 50 wounds in their bodies, ſo pittiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie were they maſſacred, thus were theſe worthie champions intercepted. The reſt of thoſe 4. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, which were not preſent at this fury of the ſpaniardes, towardes the euening, deſcended the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133399:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> hils and marched into the towne. Preſently after this, watch was appointed in al places of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne, and ſome of the ſoldiours began to dig the ground, to ſeeke for ſuch goods as the Spaniardes had buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but at that inſtant they founde nothing, except only certain pipes of wine.</p>
            <p>About the ſunne ſetting was brought in a ſpaniſh priſoner, which was deliuered to the Proueſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal, by the Generals commandement, to the end he might bring them to all ſuch places in the Ilande, whereas the Spaniardes had hidden their goods. But becauſe nothing could then be effected by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the euening approched, and it began to bee too dark, the Spaniard was committed to a keeper vntill the next morning for the purpoſe aforeſaide. But the night being far ſpent, &amp; the keeper taking ſmall regard to his charge, the Spaniard ſecretlie ſtole away and ran to the mouniaines.</p>
            <p>The 14. of Iuly, in the morning the long boates rowed againe to the ſhore, and caried aboorde ſuch goods as the enemy had left behind them, which for the moſt part were wines, for they had caried clean away all other things into the mountains, and had left almoſt nothing in the towne, but only the wines which they had buried in the earth: In the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone our people found 3. bels, which they had buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fields, where corne had growne.</p>
            <p>The 15. of Iuly, in the morning our people running vp to the hils 10. or 12. in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany to hunt &amp; ſeeke for pillage, were ſuddainly inuironed by the enemy, and 6. or 8. of them ſlaine; the reſt ſaued themſelues by flight. About noone there was a generall muſter taken of all the ſoldiours, to ſee how many wee had loſt: and ſuch ſhips as were appointed to returne home, began to deliuer out the victuals. The ſame day were two copper peeces founde: whereof the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:133399:13"/> one was 16. foot and halfe long, and the other about 14. foot.</p>
            <p>The 16. day in the morning the Lord Generall gaue notice to all captaines to reſort to him aboord his ſhip, becauſe ſome of the captaines had not ſent victuals vnto the ſoldiors that were on land, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſuffered hunger, and ſundry of the ſoldiours had complained to the General thereof: At after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, the enemy came to the hill which lieth ouer the towne, crying and calling vnto our men to come and fetch againe their muſkets, and towards the euening many marriners with their weapons lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and at that inſtant alſo all things were ordered to march very early the next morning vp the hils to fetch againe our muſkets, caliuers, and other wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, which the Spaniards before had in mockery, and gibing wiſe willed vs to fetch from them. But now when all things were ordered for this ſeruice: the ſame night aroſe a ſtrong gale of winde, encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing more and more, that in the ende it grewe to a mightie tempeſt, that notwithſtanding our fleet did ride vnder the Iland <hi>Gomera</hi> in the road before the towne, ſome were forced to way their anchors and to put to ſea, to preuent the miſchiefe like to happen to the ſhips, by reaſon they lay ſo neere one another. And when thoſe ſhips were a little way in the Sea, they caſt their anchors, and there remained. By this occaſion the generals aforeſaid enterpriſe was kept backe: we iudging it as a warning, that the Generall ſhould ſpare and preſerue his people from the bloud-thirſty ſpaniards, which had their holes and dens in the hils, and perhaps might haue taken away many of our liues. And heere by the way; by the name of the Iland <hi>Canaria,</hi> the Spaniards may rightly bee called <hi>Canarians</hi> or <hi>Canes,</hi> for <hi>Canaria</hi> is by interpretation, dogs kinde, for they ran as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:133399:14"/> ſwift as dogs, and were as tyrannicall and bloud-thirſty as the rauening Wolfe, or any other wild beaſt, which they ſufficiently manifeſted, for as ſoon as they could lay handes on any of our people (like vnto mad curs, agreeing with their name <hi>Canaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi>) they would preſently woary them.</p>
            <p>The 17. this hurtfull night ended, and the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt ouer paſſed, and alaid, the couragious ſoldiors were all in readines, deſirous to execute this peece of ſeruice, exſpecting &amp; deſiring nothing more, then to march vp the hils, and to incounter their ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous enemies. But vpon good conſideration, this enterpriſe was ſtaied, and ſome 300. ſoldiours ſent into the ſame valley, where 3. daies before our people had beene ſuddainly compaſſed, intrapped, and ſlaine by the Spaniards. Our ſoldiours being come to the valley aforeſaid found no reſiſtance, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could once ſee a ſpaniard; but found a ſmal peece of braſſe about a fadome long, and two barrels of gunpowder; and when our ſouldiours perceiued that there was no good to bee done (forbearing to mount the hils, becauſe they had no commiſſion ſo to do) with ſuch thinges as they had they returned into the towne. The euening now approching, the Generall commanded to carry aboord the ſhips, ſuch goods as they had there found, and digged out of the ground, which was accordingly done and accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, among which things were three braſſe peeces, ſome bels and other goods.</p>
            <p>Sunday the 18. of Iuly, we remained at anchor in the road of the Iland <hi>Gomera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Munday the 19. of Iuly, remaining yet in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>Gomera,</hi> and ſeeing that the Spaniardes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in their ſecret holes, and dens of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, wee ſet fire on the towne, and as neere as we could burnt down all places, as Cloiſters chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133399:14"/> hermitages and houſes, remaining yet in the towne vntill it was noone. After that all this was accompliſhed; we the vnited ſoldiours forſooke the towne, and preſently the Lord General, with al his company, went aboord the ſhips. Thus we left the Iland <hi>Gomera</hi> burning, which was neuer before done by any nation. The Spaniardes ſeeing that the ſoldiours were departed out of the Iland, with all ſpeed poſſible, in great heapes came running out of their ſecret caues and holes, to quench the fire, like as they of <hi>Allegona</hi> in the Iland of great <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> before had done.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday the 20. of Iuly, we lay ſtil in the road before <hi>Gomera,</hi> in this time 2. of our ſoldiours were put into captain <hi>Cloiers</hi> ſhip, and in lew of them, we receiued out of his ſhip 2. others, which were hurt, with two Spaniards.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <head>The ſummary or briefe declaration of the Admirals departing towardes the Weſt-Indies.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>After that the Generall had left the Ilands, he giueth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the fleete, taketh his leaue of all the Captaines and officers in moſt honorable ſort: he aduanceth the voyage to the Weſt Indies with his Nauy: the reſt of the ſhips returne into the low Countries, euery one from whence he came.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>AFter that the Iland of great <hi>Canaria</hi> was by the vnited ſoldiours taken, and won by force of Armes, and the Iland <hi>Gomera</hi> conquered, for ſundry reaſons they were forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, after they had caried to their ſhips ſuch things as they found, fired the townes, churches, cloiſters, and houſes, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their Caſtles. The Lord Generall commanded
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133399:15"/> all Captaines and officers of the fleete to reſorte vnto him aboord his ſhip. The ſame principals being come accordingly, he welcommed them and ſhewed them al friendſhip he could, thanking them for their good and faithfull endeuours which they had ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this ſeruice, which he performed with a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar oration, praying Almighty God that he woulde vouchſafe to be his only loadſman, &amp; merciful defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in all his enterpriſes, to the honor of his name, and happy ſucceſſe of the vnited Netherlandiſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces. After this, the lorde Generall againe in moſt friendly ſort, and kind ſpeeches, perſwaded &amp; deſired all the ſaide captaines and officers, (allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging many reaſons and examples) to perſeuer in their good beginning of true and faithfull ſeruice for God, and for their good Lords and principall magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, the honorable gentlemen and ſtates of the vnited Netherland; &amp; to the good liking of their vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant &amp; high borne gentleman, &amp; gouernour General prince <hi>Mauritz,</hi> their principall lorde and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp;c. with theſe and ſuch like matters the daie was ſpent.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday the 21. of Iuly, the wind was nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly: The lord Generall commanded all the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and officers to reſort vnto him: and in moſt curteous maner againe the ſecond time, tooke his leaue of them all, ordaining and appointing in his place as Admirall Generall ouer all thoſe ſhippes which were to returne home, the valiant captaine <hi>Ian Gerbrantſon,</hi> deſiring and ſtraightly charging them al there preſent, to ſhew all obedience and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vnto him, as to his owne perſon, and that they ſhould make his minde knowne to all others which had not beene there preſent. After theſe ſpeeches, and leaue taken, the Admirall <hi>Ian Gerbrantſon</hi> put out the princes colours in the maine top: and the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133399:15"/> honorable gentleman <hi>Peter von der Doeſt</hi> preſentlie cauſed the princes flag alſo to be ſpread;<note place="margin">The Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh fleet diuide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into two companies, whereof the one returneth homewardes, and the other proceedeth for the weſt Indians.</note> and as ſoone as the ſunne was ſouthweſt, all the ſhips at one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant waied their anchors, &amp; hoiſed their ſailes, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king leaue nowe the thirde time one of an other, in moſt braue and triumphant ſort, and in this maner departed the one from the other. The lord General with his fleet, ſet this courſe ſouth ſouthweſt with 36. ſhips, and the Admirall <hi>Ian Gerbrantſon</hi> ran eaſt by the wind, with 35. ſhips, with intent to returne home.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday the 18 of Auguſt, ſixteene ſhips of our fleet which were ſent to returne home, being in company together in the latitude of 36. degrees and 10. minutes, the wind ſouthweſt ſailing north<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt, before it was noone, we perceiued 2 ſtrange ſhips vnder ſaile comming out of the northweſt, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards whom we made,<note place="margin">Two Spaniſh prizes taken.</note> and at afternoone we ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke them, and made them our priſes: they were both Spaniardes, the one was a ſmall Barke, and came from Cape <hi>de Blanco</hi> in 21. degrees, loaden for <hi>Woluis</hi> in the <hi>Condate</hi> where they dwelled. In the ſame ſhips was a marchant of <hi>Cyuill</hi> with 47. men, each of their ſhips hauing two caſt peeces and euery man his muſket, but they made no ſhewe of defence, or offending. There was alſo found laden in the ſame ſhips, ſixty thouſand drie hides or ſkins, eſteemed to bee worth 6000. duckets as they repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, there were alſo found two bags with mony, in the one was 11. hundred ſingle rials, and in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 10. hundred &amp; forty ſingle rials, with two Buts of traine oile, and two barrels of gum Arabique.</p>
            <p>Thurſday the 19 day, we the aboueſaid 16. ſhips were together, beſide the two ſpaniſh ſhips, 4. ſhips of war of north <hi>Holland,</hi> 4 ſhips of <hi>Warres</hi> of <hi>Zeland</hi> and one ſhip of war of the <hi>Maze:</hi> the captain wherof
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:133399:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> was <hi>Antony Leonardſon,</hi> al the reſt were victualers. The wind weſt northweſt, we ſailed northeaſt, and by north in 36. degrees and 45. minutes. The cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines had beene all aboord the Admirall in councell aduiſing what were beſt to bee done in this matter of the Spaniards priſes.</p>
            <p>Saturday, Sunday, the 21. and 22. of Auguſt, our ſaid fleet of 18. ſhips kept yet together, we found our ſelues to bee in 39. degrees, 6. minuts. The ſun ſouth and by weſt, the winde blew vp at weſt north weſt, wee ſailed north. northeaſt, and north and by eaſt, <hi>Lysborne</hi> was eaſt of vs.</p>
            <p>Munday the ſixt of September, the winde we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterly, we ran eaſt, at noone wee ſounded, the depth was 50. fadome water, we found ſmall white ſhels with needles therein, in the hight of 49. degrees 20. minuts, the ſun ſouthweſt, wee had ſight of <hi>Vſhant,</hi> we ran northeaſt and by north.</p>
            <p>Tueſday the 7. of September, the ſun eaſt ſouth eaſt, wee ſaw England, a mighty bluſtering gale of winde from the ſouth ſouthweſt, wee ſailed north northeaſt. The ſunne ſouthweſt, came to lande at <hi>Gawſtert.</hi> Afterwarde wee turned and ſailed eaſt ſoutheaſt: In the euening it blewe ſo much winde, that wee were forced to ſtrike our maine top maſt, and we ranne the whole night with two courſes by the wind.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday the 8. of September, the foule wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther continued, the ſunne eaſt and by ſouth, we had ſight of the <hi>Ile of Wight</hi> north northweſt of vs, and ranne the whole day eaſt northeaſt with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile by the wind: as the euening approched we ſaw <hi>Beuerſier,</hi> in the night and ſecond quarter we paſſed by <hi>Douer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Turſday the 9. of September, as ſoone as the daie began to appeare it was calme weather, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:133399:16"/> darke, the ſun ſoutheaſt, we lay ſtill before <hi>Newport</hi> all the ebbe. The wind eaſterly, in the after noone the wind came northweſt, we ſet ſaile againe, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning al night by the wind with our foreſaile,</p>
            <p>Friday the 10. of September, 1599. by the break of day wee were before the <hi>Maze,</hi> the ſun ſouthweſt, we arriued by the helpe of Gods mercy and grace before the <hi>Brill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then, there is arriued at <hi>Texell</hi> another ſhip of war, whereof one <hi>Cater</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> was captain, the wich was ſeuered from the fleet in this voiage by tempeſt, and thought to be loſt. The ſaid captaine met with ſome priſes, and in company of two engliſh ſhippes tooke a Caruell of <hi>Aduiſo,</hi> verie richly laden comming out of <hi>India,</hi> and hauing more men then the engliſh, ſhared halfe of the goods with them, and ſo came home this preſent month of <hi>Octob.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:133399:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133399:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133399:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
